[Music]
and welcome to the meta meta petting zoo
episode number two I believe it's
episode number two it could be any
episode you want by the time we listen
to this but we'll say it's two for the
purposes of this show my name is Abbey
aka hair boat here on the stack overflow
Stack Exchange sites I'm here with John
and Juan as as we were last time let's
all maybe go around and introduce
ourselves again for the folks at home
who maybe don't know how amazing and
wonderful you guys are starting with one
hi what's up somebody was fun M I am one
of the community managers here I am NOT
John but I am Juan in case anybody is
wondering and yeah happy to be here in
our second our second episode John
firstly I am John and not one you know
how in like Spanish class you were all
supposed to like I don't know if you had
to do this one but I had to come up with
my Spanish name and it was always one
and I was like I don't want to be one I
just wanted John I convinced people that
I was Jonathan oh that's what it should
be
not that I'm happy as I said I am
neither John nor Juan when I was in
French class in middle school I had to
pick a French name and I went with Emily
because that was my sister's name is
Emily and there's a French version of
that there is no French version of Abby
or Abigail as far as I know although my
nickname my mom used to call me as a kid
a babe which is the French word for be
like a like a bumblebee because I used
to I used to talk a lot and be really
annoying and also it sounded like my
name so I was a I was a bumblebee and
she could tell me to to buzz off maybe
that was so you can call me Abby or
or Emily or hey you or buzz off or or
whatever if you like
speaking of bumblebees and buzzing off
we're gonna talk about moderation today
okay I'm going with maybe so as everyone
listening to this probably knows
definitely knows you probably are a
moderator if you're listening to this
honestly or our audience is fairly
limited we rely on our moderators
throughout the network to keep things
moving keep things running keep things
clean and simple but also just keep the
communities kind of tightly knitted and
working together really well so we
wanted to take a little bit of time
today to talk about moderators
moderation what do they do what should
they do what do they need from us what
do we do for them etcetera
so I guess the first thing we got to do
is define our terms right that's where
you start and so starting by actors
functionary suits Webster's dictionary
defines a moderator as so yeah we will
start with the non dictionary definition
of moderator just kind of what what what
is a mod here at Stack Exchange Stack
Overflow what do they do
what what what does moderation been like
through the ages and yeah what have you
guys observe starting with John yeah so
when when the site first started one of
the things that it was built on is the
idea that you know everyone is working
together to produce this content and a
lot of the traditional roles of of
moderators went to other people in the
community so like a lot of places you
can't edit other people's posts but a
moderator can and around here anybody
can edit well you can at least suggest
an edit for a post and so there were a
lot of things that were intended to be
done by by regular users but then you
kind of you know there were there's
always exceptional cases right so okay
fixing a typo well you don't need to be
super specialized to do that but what if
you have someone who is constantly
trying to you know sell their product
sort of sneakily within an answer how do
you deal with that person or you know
just sort of exceptional situations that
are beyond the capacity of you know most
people in the community need someone
with a little bit
more specialization so that was I think
the original idea of moderators they
would be we used to call them exception
handlers or we call them exception
handlers because these are exceptional
situations unusual situations
ramaa Network interesting so guys I'm
coming from a foreign background where a
moderator does not does not function in
the same way as a moderator functions
here in our network at Stack Overflow
and the stock exchange network and so
typically what we would do when when
looking at a moderator we were we would
look at individuals who a were
trustworthy B were were almost as a
super user right somebody who was highly
engaged in the community so I'm going to
had good reputation amongst their peers
someone who was contributing someone who
was who was definitely a user that
brought value to to the community and
and when when moderation issues come up
typically what it is is you know the
removal of spam things being posted that
are inappropriate content that is not
wanted but then also also dealing with
with squabbles between between users you
know arguments things like that and so
you know we would we would want to look
for individuals that had these kinds of
skill sets to where you know they showed
passion and they showed integrity and
they also had a level mind and an
ability to communicate well at least
that's in my mind when I think of a
moderator I think of someone who is
definitely an exception handler but also
someone who is going to possess a degree
of skill and in in I don't know we'll
call it peopling right yeah just mad
vigils that that's going to help with
the community grow and be at peace does
that does that sound like like like what
we're doing here yeah yeah I think so
John I was I was about to ask you how if
you feel like our current moderation
procedures are the way that we find
moderators are we optimizing for the
same thing as what one's describing from
from other communities or what do you
think you know that's interesting we had
for many years we had a system where
sites that had been graduated would
would run elections
and so it's actually other people in the
community who are finding the moderators
or who are picking among the nominees
and for a long time the beta sites the
sites that hadn't reached graduation yet
community managers would actually
appoint people and I think when I was
appointing people regularly all those
things that one was talking about were
things I was definitely looking at
especially for a smaller site the people
interaction and the sort of leadership
stuff that's probably even more
important than being able to handle a
bunch of flags
so on stackoverflow like exception
handling is the real big thing because
you've got you know just thousands of
flags set to churn through and on a
small site you might only get you know a
handful of flags in a week but you also
have a community conflict and so when
when we were running when I was
appointing moderators that's the sort of
the same sort of person that one was
talking about I think yeah that's that's
something I've never really considered
is so we've we've long known that
there's kind of two different theories
of moderation there's the soli exception
handler you know handling flags and
doing things the community can't do and
then there's this other leadership role
that's kind of better at people enroll
like one has been describing and I had
never made the connection until you said
that just now that there's different
communities have different needs at
different points in their life cycles so
they need often a little bit of flag
handling exception handling whatever but
if they're smaller like you're
describing when we when we were
appointing Pro Tem moderators they need
a lot more of that designated leadership
it's harder for that kind of activity to
just bubble up when the activity overall
on the site is so much lower and so we
need a little boost from us to say hey
you're thinking in the right direction
you know step up and kind of take a
little bit of ownership here and that
really encourages people to to help the
site coalesce so that that's kind of a
distinction I never really made that
maybe the needs change over the course
of a site's life cycle and we should
think about incorporating that into our
process why no I was gonna I was going
to ask you in
experience with you know tons of other
online communities have you ever
encountered elections on any other kind
of community engine or forum or anything
like that yeah this is something that is
that is more more uncommon at least with
the experience that I've had more so
because the the placement of moderators
in that position was one that an
administrator would do a community
manager and so depending on depending on
the kind of community that the structure
would be administrator at least within
the system the backends the backend
system we have administrators you'd have
moderators you would have super users
you would have regular users and then
you could designate a bunch of different
categories of users like you could have
a certain part of your sites that only
certain people can access like if you
had a marketplace right you would do
verification all those people that have
filled out the application been verified
would get that that permission to enter
that specific part of the site and so
giving permissions was a big deal and so
the administrator which could be the the
community manager in my experience would
appoint the moderators they would be the
ones to to place these individuals in
that position because you're talking
about working within a team and so it
isn't just you know clean up do do you
know do spam removal or you know send
people their passwords or send them you
know a link or so it it involved a bit
more interacting with the community it
involved talking with them and sharing a
vision it involved getting them to
buy-in into a direction that the
community was going to be moving into it
involved discussing any features that
they wanted there was there was a sense
of a team within the within the
administration if you will and so here
at sac overflow one of the one of the
things I had to really get accustomed to
is that elections are a big thing and
they're important I see the value of it
here totally see it but also that the
way that we work between and maybe it's
a topic we can we can discuss in the
future what is a responsibility of a cm
to a moderator because we talk a lot
about the the responsibility of a
moderator at least as this is one of the
topics we're doing but internally we
just
Gus a lot about what a moderator should
do but what are what are some of the
things that the CMS are responsible to
the moderators for and so here it seems
like the moderators really are they're
brought up from the community which I
think it's great they're there their
peer reviewed their peer elected they
know the system but really what they're
doing is they are handling exception
cases very very few yet to see a an
increase of a of a team like environment
to where the community manager will sit
with the moderators and discuss the
vision of the site will discuss the
direction the future you know plans
things like that in and granted you so
everybody knows there's only a handful
of community managers as compared to the
number of moderators so it is it's
physically impossible and then with the
changes that have gone on within the
company I mean is it makes it really
hard it's not that it's not that we
don't want to I just I'd like to see
that shift a little bit so from my
experience answer your question Abbey is
election was something that that was
done not very frequently mainly
moderators were appointed by the
administrator or the community manager
so good John I was thinking there this
is something I hadn't thought of but
when I was a user and a moderator on a
small site we did sometimes have those
discussions where we would sit down with
a community manager and say listen this
is where site is this is where we want
it to go we even had a full Oh site
evaluation process that we would try to
do we have 170 something sites now and
we haven't grown our community team as
fast as we've grown ourselves so I I
definitely see that as something I'd
like to improve on is is have you know
if we're asking our moderators to be
leaders on their site like let's help
them be be leaders on the site in the
various ways that we can you know and
not just focus on you know how many
flags can you handle this month
whatever yeah and go back to go back and
hit at a point that you made John I
think I think depending on the life
cycle as we mentioned depending on where
the community is whether you appoint or
elect I think it's crucial when the
community as young as we know if the
community is young still trying to
figure out who they are what the main
topics are going to be what's accepted
what's not it's I think I think it's
important have a community manager
appoint a moderator there's there's more
communication there about what's
expected and then once a community gets
going like we do in the life cycle of
the site's we allow the community to
select from among their from among their
peers but I think even through all of
that we are looking for individuals and
those that are moderators on our sites
we like to believe and to think that
they're individuals that are that are
definitely invested in the communities
they have a lot to share their knowledge
is there I would like to see us increase
in in our in our communication with them
I know communication is is is increasing
now it's not like it hasn't been there
and I saw like moderators aren't saying
hey we really need these features or hey
what about this we know that there they
are in fact asking what when I say
increase I mean more I'd like to see the
community management team engage more
with them with again the caveat that
because there's so few of us it's it's
it's a lot of work to go through each
eat each and every sign yeah one thing
that occurs to me is I as I listen to
you guys talk about this is how much
we've been able to achieve at this scale
because we've figured out lots of ways
to automate automate a lot of the work
that community managers of other styles
of community might have to do not just
moderation you know we do have a lot of
literal automation for moderation you
know cleaning up voting vote fraud and
finding spam and stuff like that there
are a lot of robots that do that work
for us but also automation in terms of
you know elections are an automated
process for for finding the people who
are moderators we're going to do those
exceptions and also the whole reputation
system that gives people access to other
tools other privileges you know we don't
have a concept of you know a super user
or special access or whatever like like
you were describing on other sites one
but we have we have privileges we have
if you hit this level you know you can
see this these stats
use these tools or whatever and that's a
direct function of your reputation which
is an automated things are so beautiful
and they work so well I'm very fortunate
to be working within a platform that
allows those things to happen because
now it's not just the moderator who's
gonna get pinged and said hey this
person said this or they posted their
phone number by accident or their credit
card number or their home address can
you go in and remove it and nobody can
go in and edit a question except for the
moderator and again they're always going
to be the minority so it's great that we
have those privileges I think that's
that's a fantastic feature yes it's
definitely what's enabled us to to scale
to have as many sites as we have and to
have the sites that we have that are
very active to let them be as active as
they are but I think the cost of that is
what you guys are describing there's a
little bit less interaction between the
community team obviously it's very small
and there's a scale issue there but we
have we rely on our users obviously and
these automation processes to get get
the stuff done that needs to get done
which is great and it's wonderful that
it happens but also we're less connected
and we've we've over the years kind of
drifted a little further away from the
communities that's one reason why we're
doing this podcast is to to put some
human speech you know facial recognition
or voice recognition or whatever back in
the in the mix here so that we can be
more connected and get to know each
other a little bit better or at least
you know this is one way you guys are
get to know us a little better but we'd
love for it to go the other way - John
Regan is I was about to say maybe in
future episodes we could interview
moderators whoo that's a great idea this
is a call for you know requests for
proposals if you'd like to be
interviewed on this podcast you can call
1-800 we do not have a phone number set
up this is a very low-budget podcast we
have a couple minutes left I'd love to
know if either of you have any thoughts
about you know we talked a little bit
about how you would like to see the
relationship between moderators and
community managers evolve a little bit
we'd love to see some more communication
what are some other ways you'd like to
see moderation at Stack Exchange evolved
what's kind of what do you feel like is
the future of moderation here I think
for me we have
this concept of you are once your
moderator you're always a moderator and
it's not been easy for people to sort of
slip out of the job and we've done a few
things in the past like giving them an
opportunity to take a vacation like
there's a there's a feature for I'm not
going to be at the site for a while but
I'd really like to see more ways that we
can give people the freedom to say I no
longer I'm interested in watering the
site and they can just do that and you
know you they can always contact us now
but it's sort of a like all right well
you contact us and then we're gonna set
up an election and can you wait until
we're done with the election and all
that sort of thing and it'd be nice if
we could put some more structure around
just you know I'm I'm done this is a
phase of my life and I'm I'm no longer
interested in in being a moderator yeah
I think it's a human thing's pretty good
you know right it's just mm-hmm yeah we
go through phases we go through you know
I'm still interested and engaged in this
community but I have less time or you
know I'm want to focus on asking and
answering questions instead of
moderating or whatever it's a natural
part of being a member of a community if
your relationship with you know a person
or a community or yourself or your
family or whatever if that relationship
isn't evolving over time then you know
that's that's stagnation that's kind of
a problem and we've we've been at this
for 10 years and so everyone's
relationship should be changing and
evolving and if that means stepping back
for moderation great if that means you
want to become a moderate or get more
involved great but we need to have that
flexibility to allow people to to grow
and change and have their interests
evolve just like just like in any other
community or any other type of activity
what about you on what do you see what
you wanna see in the future I would I
would like to see the role of the
moderator expand to one of an individual
who is who is who is living was a living
example of what a good member are to be
so not just somebody who's competent in
the technical in the technical aspects
of moderation but also someone who is
who's worthy of emulation so to speak
somebody who you can who you can follow
someone that you can trust someone that
that that is you know
an evangelist for our site someone that
can that can guide new members someone
that is you know breath of fresh air
somebody who can inspire others and who
is so affectionate about the community
that it just it just you know everybody
gets you know easiest contagious or
she's contagious everybody everybody has
the same feeling because this individual
is moderating so more than just you know
the ins and outs of you know removing
cleaning fixing editing all that but
also somebody who is who is really you
know engaged in a level to where they're
able to bring and inspire others to to
participate more to to you know to write
more into edit more to answer more to
you know all that I'd like to see the
role of a moderator expand to that to
those meta aspects to a little bit of a
mascot almost or a personally around and
inspiring somebody look up to sure yeah
sure that's really beautiful sure well
on that note and speaking of moderators
John do we have a sponsor for this week
yeah I did get a sponsorship request
right at the just of the last minute
here and the sponsor is is very
important on the site already but we
just want to you know they want to raise
their visibility a little bit and remind
people about who they are and this is
the the moderator diamond every
moderator on every site has a little
diamond next to their name and it's
there to remind you that this is the
person you know perhaps to look up to us
as one was talking about we've got a lot
of great people who already have
diamonds next to their name and and so
we want to show that they have that
commitment by putting a little symbol
next to their name and then the diamond
also can sometimes signify employees and
you know that can get confusing because
you've got moderators and employees but
but the diamond shows that even our
employee our employees are on you know
they're not some super high level person
beyond moderators in fact a lot of our
employees have diamonds and don't do any
moderation at all they just have it
there so that they can take care of a
few things on the site so we response
by the diamond all diamonds next to the
moderator name it's like we always say
diamonds are immediately know I actually
I thought it was talking and I had to
refrain from from bursting it out until
he was in on that note with that
incredible joke that everyone loves and
made nobody groan I think we should call
it it's it's been a wonderful 22 22 and
a half minutes 23 by the time I'm done
talking I'm gonna do Joel's outro you've
gone and wasted another 22 minutes of
your life listening to the meta petting
zoo podcast thanks for hanging out with
us and we will talk to you next time
[Music]